<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The interest of the English nation under the happy government of King William III once more asserted in answer to the challenge of a Jacobite : wherein is proved that the law which forbids taking up arms against the King upon any pretence whatsoever is consistent with the late revolution / by Philo-kalo-basileos.</title>
            <author>Philo-kalo-basileos.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25207</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08793805</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08793805</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41855</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1262:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The interest of the English nation under the happy government of King William III once more asserted in answer to the challenge of a Jacobite : wherein is proved that the law which forbids taking up arms against the King upon any pretence whatsoever is consistent with the late revolution / by Philo-kalo-basileos.</title>
                  <author>Philo-kalo-basileos.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by E. Whitlock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>The challenge of a Jacobite answered--A defence of the foregoing discourse against certain exceptions communicated in writing.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41855:1"/>
            <p>The INTEREST OF <hi>The English Nation</hi> Under the Happy Government OF King William III. Once more Aſſerted: In ANSWER to the <hi>Challenge of a Iacobite.</hi> WHEREIN IS PROVED <hi>That that Law which forbids taking up Arms against the King upon any Pretence whatſoever, is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the late Revolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Philo-Kalo-Baſileos.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>If we take the whole People as one Body and Maſs, then as the Head is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the Body, and not the Body for the Head; ſo muſt a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous King know himſelf ordained for his People, and not his People for him.</hi> 
               <bibl>King <hi>James</hi> I. his Speech to both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>March</hi> 19. 1603.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by <hi>E. Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall,</hi> by <hi>Amen-Corner.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41855:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41855:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>EVer ſince our Glorious Monarch King <hi>William</hi> came to the Crown, <hi>I</hi> have made it my Buſineſs upon all occaſions to the utmoſt of my Power and Capacity, to Aſſert his Intereſt, and to ſet forth the Happineſs of theſe Kingdoms, together with my own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction under his Government.—To this purpoſe I have written ſeveral Papers, ſome of which were loſt in the Crowd, when they were by Learned Hands recommended to the Publick, and others have been neglected, and thrown aſide as inconſiderable; and yet for all that I am not diſcouraged: For I find ſo much Pleaſure in the Cauſe <hi>I</hi> am Defending, and ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment in diverting my ſelf with Political Reflections in this Auſpicious Reign, that however I may fail in the Management, I ſhall never be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in my Zeal and Hearty Endeavours to Support and Maintain the preſent Government.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt, the following Diſcourſe, together with the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, was extorted from me by the inſolent Prating, and undecent Scribling of certain <hi>Jacobites,</hi> one of which would needs urge upon me the following Caſe, which he preſumed to be ſuch a Capping Queſtion as no Body could Anſwer. I ſay it was extorted from me at that Time, being unwilling to engage in a Debate with my Neighbours; and having beſides other things under Conſideration. For though ſuch Rencounters are a Pleaſure and Diverſion to me, at a proper Seaſon, yet when other Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is before me, or when my Mind is Cloudy, I am willing enough to leave theſe Debates to better Hands; being ſenſible that what is mean at beſt, muſt be yet meaner under ſuch Circumſtances. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which account the <hi>Reader</hi> will not ſind here ſo even a Thread of Diſcourſe, as might be Expected. But that I little value, not ſeeking my own Credit, but the Security of the Government.</p>
            <p>Had I begun to write about the Diſcovery of the Plot, it might perhaps have ſharpened: he Dulneſs of my Pen, and inſpir'd a Creeping Style with Life and Vigour; but I was not ſo happily Tim'd. And even now when the Snare is broken, it is a better Seaſon for Rejoycing and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, than for Satyr and Invective: For the <hi>Jacobites</hi> have left us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay; their Actions ſtrike us Dumb; and their Bloody Deſigns cry ſo loud, that nothing can be heard. They have indeed been ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb facs="tcp:41855:3"/>already, but this Plot has painted them more Black and Monſtrous, more Loathſome and Abominable than any thing that has been ſaid, or could be thought of heretofore. And if <hi>Oldham</hi> were alive again, he would be confounded with the Subject, and not know where to begin his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. They are a Generation Proflig ate and Abſurd beyond the Examples of former Ages, and made up of ſuch Heterogeneous Stuff, that they are perfectly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>naccountable. but may they never ſucceed better in their Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and we ſhall the better forgive them; eſpecially ſince Vengeance is waiting for them, and Providence ſeems abhorrent of their Villany. And ſince they have left the Church becauſe a Proteſtant King is there Prayed for, it is but <hi>Decorum,</hi> that they ſhould Reform their Devotions, and, to their Prayers for K. <hi>James,</hi> add this for themſelves,
<q>
                  <l>Vos O mihi manes,</l>
                  <l>Eſte boni, quoniam ſuperis averſa Voluntas.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>After all, it is to be hoped, that the <hi>Jacobites</hi> will divide their Forces; and ſome that have not yet made Shipwrack of Shame and Modeſty, may come over to our Party; others will be for making Apologies, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſhift the Odium of the Plot off from themſelves; others may grow deſperate, if they think fit, and rage like the Devil, when he has but a a ſhort time to reign; and ſome will fret and fry in their own Greaſe, like a certain Brother of theirs, mentioned by the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Qui Centum vinctus ahenis,</l>
                  <l>Poſt tergum nodis, fremet horridus ore Cruento.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But I now leave them, either to the Gallows, or at leaſt the Diſcipline of their own wicked Minds, and the ſecret Laſhes of an Evil Conſcience.</p>
            <q>Occultum quatiente animo tortore flagellum.</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41855:3"/>
            <head>THE Challenge of a Jacobite ANSWERED.</head>
            <head type="sub">Which was to ſhew, <hi>How that Law which forbids taking Arms againſt the King upon any Pretence whatſoever, is Conſiſtent with the late Revolution.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the firſt place, I lay down this for a Foundation, That General Rules have, for the moſt part, ſome tacit Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which muſt of neceſſity be underſtood, tho' not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: And this is more eſpecially ſo, when the nature of the thing is ſuch, that the Exception ought not to be made, nor can be mentioned without great Inconvenience.</p>
            <p>Now two things I am obliged to do in this matter; firſt, I ſhall give ſeveral plain and undeniable Inſtances, to evince the Truth of what I have here laid down: And ſecondly, I ſhall give Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſhew that it ought to be ſo in the Caſe before us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Yet forty days, and Niniveh ſhall be overthrown,</hi> Jonah 3.4. This is poſitive and abſolute; yet here is to be underſtood, <hi>Except they Repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Children obey your Parents in all things,</hi> Epheſ. 6.1. Yet if they command ſinful things, I muſt not obey them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wives are commanded in Scripture to <hi>be ſubject to their Husbands in all things,</hi> without any Exception mentioned; yet ſtill we muſt except ſinful Commands.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Marriage obliges the Parties to live together till Death part
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41855:4"/>them; but Adultery may part them ſooner, and that Legally too.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal:</hi> This is ſpoken without any explicit Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; and yet Caſuiſts tell us, That in Caſes of extream hunger, and peril of Starving, and being deny'd all manner of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, a Man may take where he can come to it, any thing to eat or drink, for the preſervation of Life. But after the ſtrictneſs of this Precept, even the plucking Ears of Corn and eating them, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mans Field, is plain Stealing.</p>
            <p>Now as on the one hand, both Scripture and Reaſon will juſtifie theſe Exceptions; ſo on the other ſide, there is all the reaſon in the World why they ſhould not be expreſſed: For if <hi>Jonah</hi> had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> That they ſhould be deſtroyed in forty days, if they repented not; it's very like they would have delayed their Repentance: But the Terror of a Peremptory Doom wrought more effectually.</p>
            <p>If Children and Wives had been commanded Obedience with a Reſerve, it would have implied that Husbands and Parents might prove ſo wicked as to command them ſinful things, which ought not to be ſuppoſed: And then ill-diſpoſed Children might diſobey upon ſlight occaſions, and fancy all ſuch Commands to be unjuſt, as they had not a mind to obſerve.</p>
            <p>If Marriage did oblige the Parties to live together till Death or Adultery ſhould make a Separation, and that it were ſo expreſſed in the Office; this would be an odious and ſhameful Inſinuation, that one or both of them might prove ſo wicked, as to give occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Divorce.</p>
            <p>And if the Law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not ſteal, without extream Neceſſity; this would have been taken for little leſs than a Licenſe toſteal, every one judging for himſelf of his own Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Thus we may ſee how natural it is for General Words to carry along with them, a reſerved Condition or Limitation, which yet ought by no means to be Mentioned or Expreſſed. And thus it is in the Caſe before us: For if the Law had Said, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take Arms againſt the King upon any pretence whatſoever, Except the King deſignes to Subvert the Government,</hi> This would have been a Diſloyal Intimation, that the King might prove a Tyrant; and would have given Incouragment to the people to Suſpect his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41855:4"/>and many times, without any Cauſe, to Cenſure his Actions; Yet, that thus it muſt be Underſtood, will Appear by the Reaſons Following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is this, That if it be Underſtood in the Utmoſt Force and Latitude that the words will bear, it makes Void all other Laws; nay even the Law of God-cannot ſtand in its way. If you take it by the wrong handle, it will be ſo ill Condition'd as to Suffer no Law but it Self. The deſign of the Law is to ſecure to Every Man his Right. It is by Law that we attend our Callings, that we Eat and Sleep in quietneſs, that we Enjoy what we Call our Own, that we can ſerve God in Peace, and that our Churches are not turned into Idol-Temples. But now if we muſt upon no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whatſoever defend theſe Rights when they are Invaded, what benefit have we by the Law? Or to what End ſerves it? If we muſt upon no pretence whatſoever, even at the utmoſt Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, reſiſt the Illegal Proceedings of the Prince, then is the whole Law of <hi>England</hi> no more but Sham; and whatſoever we have, we enjoy it only at the Kings diſcretion, and during his pleaſure: Nay all the Societies of men in <hi>England,</hi> are no more but as ſo many Herds of Cattel to Labour for the Uſe, and to be ſlaughtered at the pleaſure of the King. So that either we muſt qualifie that Article of the Law, or give up all the reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a difference (as all men know) between the power of <hi>Making</hi> Laws, and the power of <hi>Executing</hi> the ſame; the latter reſts intirely in the King, but not the former. Now with reſpect to the Executive power, we yield (if that will pleaſe our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries) That the King is not to be reſiſted, upon any pretence whatſoever; Whilſt he is Executing the Law, no man may ſay unto him <hi>What doeſt thou?</hi> Whatever colour there may be of male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adminiſtration, that can be no Juſt ground of Reſiſtance, becauſe the Law provides a remedy, and the Miniſters muſt Anſwer for it. But then, this can never be Extended to the Legiſlative Power, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you will ſuppoſe that the Parliment when they made that Law, intended not only to Cancel all the reſt, but never to make any more. This had been a final Diſſolution of all Parliaments, and of the Goverment it ſelf: It had put all into the Kings hands, and made him Arbitrary by a Law. As if they had Enacted, <hi>Let the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41855:5"/>King henceforward make Laws without a Parliament, Let him pull down the Church and ſet up an Idol, Let him Alienate his Kingdom, and ſell his People for Slaves, or any thing elſe, what he pleaſes:</hi> Nay, if he be ſeiz'd with a Phrenzy, and Kill the People about him, he is not to be reſiſted, upon any pretence whatſoever. And if he ſhould Attempt to kill himſelf, there is no means of prevention, no touching him, no laying hands upon him, tho' it be for his Safety: See what Extremity and Abſurdity this Doctrine of our Adverſaries leads to! But if they will admitt of an Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we are Content to Divide the Truth, and let them take one half, but we will never yield the other. The King then in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Laws made according to the Conſtitution of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is not to be reſiſted on any Account whatſoever: But if they will have the King to make Laws by himſelf, and do what he pleaſes without Reſiſtance, they talk without book, and will never be Convinced till they are going to the Gallows, or to a Stake.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The King, being no more than a Man, cannot do much harm by his own proper ſtrength; ſo that ſuppoſing him to be a Tyrant, I never can fear that he will come in Perſon and take away my Life or Eſtate: He muſt then act by Commiſſioners. Now theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners muſt be duly qualified perſons, and rightly Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to Law, to do ſome legal Act. Coming then under theſe Circumſtances, they are God's Miniſters to me for my Good; in reſiſting them, I reſiſt the Ordinance of God, and muſt expect Damnation and Judgment, for ſo doing. And here again I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Jacobites</hi> and I are perfectly Agreed. But what if theſe pretended Commiſſioners ſhould happen to be Papiſts, French Dragoons, or Rapparees, and came without any legal Commiſſion, to Robb me, by vertue of a Writing, which they call a Commiſſion, under the Kings Hand and Seal, what then? Why truly then I might happen to be Robb'd or Murdered. And what ſay our Self-denying Adverſaries to this? They ſay I muſt patiently ſuffer and ſubmit; for tho' theſe perſons be not qualified according to Law, yet they Act according to the King's pleaſure, and I muſt lie at their Feet; Yes, ſo I would, if I could not help it: But ſo would I do at the Feet of High-way-men, and from them I ſhould find more Mercy. Thieves and Robbers ſpoil ſome particular
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41855:5"/>perſons: But theſe are the Villains that deſtroy Government. Were it not for theſe, the King could do no harm: They are Devouring Beaſts, and Savage Monſters broken looſe; and ought to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accordingly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſhall add in the 4th place, That the King of <hi>England</hi> is King by Law, it is by Law that he wears a Crown, and is cloathed with Royal Power: But if he Subverts the Foundation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment, he takes away the Foot he ſtands upon; he deſtroys his own Authority, and Ceaſes to be a King; He is then but like <hi>Robin-hood,</hi> an Out-law: For a King without Law, Implies a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. The Matter then in ſhort is this; The King Executing the Law is not to be reſiſted upon any pretence whatſoever; but if he lay aſide the Law, and become Arbitrary, he diveſts himſelf of his Crown and Dignity, and is no longer a King.</p>
            <p>But becauſe our Adverſaries will ſtorm heavily at this Saying, how Undeniable ſo ever it be, let us ſee if we can Strengthen it by Authority; And firſt, That of a Wiſe and Learned King, <hi>viz. James</hi> the Firſt, who in a Speech before the Parliament, 1609. has theſe words. <hi>A King Governing in a Settled Kingdom, leaves to be a King, and Degenerates into a Tyrant, as ſoon as he leaves off to Rule according to his Laws; and they that perſwade them the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, are Vipers and Peſts, both againſt them and the Commonwealth.</hi> So that it ſeems a King may fall from his Power, and ceaſe to be a King; and he actually does ſo, when he leaves off to Rule accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Laws. Let us now ſee what the force of Truth has Extorted from a Learned Man of our Adverſaries Party, a Mighty Aſſerter of Monarchical Power, the Famous <hi>Barclay. Two Caſes,</hi> he ſaies, <hi>there are, whereby a King,</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>becomes no King, and loſes all power and Regal Authority over his people, for he diveſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his Royal Crown and Dignity, he returns to the ſtate of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man, and the People become freeand Superiour.</hi> All the words in the Dictionary cannot cutt deeper than theſe, nor kill the Cauſe more Dead upon the Sport: to Add any thing, would be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction; and to offer at Illuſtration would be to darken. I ſhall only mention his two Caſes, and leave it. The firſt is, <hi>If the King Endeavour to overturn the Government, and have a purpoſe and Deſign to ruin the Kingdom and Common wealth.</hi> The Second is, <hi>If he make himſelf the Dependant of another, and betray his people into the Power
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41855:6"/>and Dominion of a forreign Nation.</hi> Theſe two Caſes are both ſo like ours of Late, that one would think this Author had written by Inſpiration: And the beſt of all is, he is taken for an Enemy, which makes his Teſtimony on our ſides the more Conſiderable.</p>
            <p>By this time I think it may appear, that <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> is not to be taken in the rigid and inflexible Sence of our Adverſaries; but ſo qualified as to let the Engliſh Frame and Conſtitution of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſtand where it is. But there is nothing, almoſt, which may not be Spoiled by overdoing: Nothing better in a well-ſettled Government than <hi>Obedience;</hi> but once miſplaced, there's nothing worſe. This is that which had it been Univerſal, had left nothing ere this day, but Grief and Lamentation, Chains and Slavery, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry, for which Poſterity might have had cauſe to Curſe the Servile Baſeneſs of the preſent Generation, had not K. <hi>William,</hi> and many Noble <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> ſtood in the Gapp, to Save the Nation from Sudden Ruine, and from a Sad Character in after times.</p>
            <p>Now let our Adverſaries ſtand ſtill a little, and Conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be not <hi>righteous overmuch Eccl.</hi> 7.16. And whether they do not make themſelves over-wiſe. I would as ſoon paſs my word for Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs, that they ſhould not be Capable of Exceſs, as any thing Elſe that I can think off. And yet even in that Caſe the wiſeſt of Kings thought a caution Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. And this is the Character of thoſe men we have to deal with; they will be wiſer than the Publick Wiſdom of the Nation; and more Righteous than the whole Church whereof they profeſs to be Members.</p>
            <p>I very well remember the time when theſe Men, above others, were Continually Charging the Diſſenters with Pride and Self-Conceit, with willful Obſtinacy, with Faction and Diſobedience; ſome could find nothing Elſe to Preach on, and others made it their common Diſcourſe; and now, <hi>out of their own mouths they are Juſtly Condemn'd.</hi> Some Diſſenters indeed have ſome needleſs Scruples about <hi>Cermonies;</hi> but Theſe only ſcruple <hi>Deliverance;</hi> and to be Saved from Ruine and Miſery, lies heavy upon their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> They pay <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> or a <hi>Non-Ens:</hi> and they return <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Ignominy</hi> for <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41855:6"/>
I ſhall conclude this matter with a Sentence taken from a very learned Pen, which alſo has been aſſerted by others; Namely, <hi>That when a Prince breaks in upon the Religion and Liberties of his People, they ought to ſtand up in their own Defence, and may alſo call in a Neighbour, or Forreigner to their Aſſiſtance.</hi> And this very thing has been Declared Lawful by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by K. <hi>James</hi> the firſt, by K. <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, with their Parliaments; and by Arch Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> into the Bargain, as may be further made Evident upon occaſion.</p>
            <p>And here I thought to have made an End; But I find our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, when other reaſons fail them, betake themſelves to the Bible, wherein they think to find their Unlimitted <hi>Power</hi> and paſſive <hi>Obedience.</hi> I cannot pretend to Remember all thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Scripture, which they have Preſs'd for this Service; but two or three of the more remarkable, I ſhall Endeavour at preſent to Releaſe from the Unnatural force and Violence put upon them, and the reſt as I meet with them.</p>
            <p>Firſt Prov. 30.31. A <hi>King againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi> I grant it, in the Sence afore-mentioned: That is, So long as he remains a <hi>King,</hi> and Keeps the Laws, he is a <hi>Rebel</hi> that oppoſes him: But when he falls from that, he is a <hi>Rebel</hi> himſelf. I ſpeak not this at Random, but I'll make it good. The firſt <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a <hi>Rebel,</hi> if you will believe the Prophet <hi>Samuel:</hi> For he plainly Charges him with <hi>Rebellion. Behold</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>to obey is better than Sacrifice, and to harken than the fat of Rams: For Rebellion is as the Sin of Witchcraft &amp;c.</hi> 1. Sam. 15.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> had given a Command to <hi>Saul,</hi> that he ſhould Smite <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck</hi> and Deſtroy utterly all that they had. This was the Law he was to obſerve: But he diſobeyed it, and thereupon the Prophet not only gives him a ſevere Reprimand, but <hi>Saul</hi> left his Kingdom beſide. After this, <hi>David</hi> was ſo far from <hi>Nonreſiſtance,</hi> that he Armed himſelf in his own Defence, and about 600 Men. And he Seiz'd upon Strong-holds at <hi>Engedi.</hi> Tis true, <hi>David would not Kill him Cowardly,</hi> which was a Noble and brave Example, but had he met him fairly in the Field, no doubt but he would have Fought him. He gave him at one time ſuch a Lecture as made him fall a weeping: At another time he preach't to him from the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41855:7"/>top of an Hill, ſo long till <hi>Saul</hi> Propheſied <hi>David</hi>'s Succeſs, and the ruine of his own Kingdom. <hi>Thou ſhalt both doe great things, and alſo ſhalt prevail.</hi> 1. Sam. 26.25. Now all this being done by <hi>David</hi> in a poſture of Defence, and probably with <hi>Goliah</hi>'s Sword in his hand, amounts ſufficiently to a Riſing up againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> and Conſequently that theſe words are not to be taken Strictly, but in ſuch a qualified ſence as may comport with other parts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as will further appear by conſidering another Text here following, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Who may ſay unto a King what doeſt thou?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the former Scripture our Adverſaries would bind our hands, and with this they would tye our tongues: The one muſt deprive us of Self Defence, and the other of the Liberty of Speech. It is not Enough to Suffer unjuſtly and to be deſtroyed, but it is a Crime to Complain, or to repreſent our Grievances. How unlike are ſome <hi>Earthly Gods</hi> to the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> whoſe Authority they have, and whom they ought to Reſemble! He invites, nay he Commands us to petition him for what we want. They Cannot bear to be petition'd at all, but call it <hi>Rebellion.</hi> He will not ſuffer us to be tempted beyond what we are able to bear: They will take our Fields and Vineyards, make us Slaves and Beggars, and we may not enquire the reaſon.</p>
            <q>
               <l>En quo diſcordia Cives</l>
               <l>Perduxit miſeros! En queis conſevimus agros!</l>
            </q>
            <p>Such was the Effect of Court Flattery, that none muſt look into the Kings Meaſures, nor dare to ask a Queſtion: None muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him of Danger, reprove him of Evil, nor adviſe him for Good; for <hi>who may ſay unto him, What doeſt thou? Counſellors</hi> and <hi>Chaplains</hi> (at this rate) muſt all take their leave, there's no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or buſineſs for them. This indeed was lately our Caſe, and thus our Adverſaries would have it ſtill.</p>
            <p>But by their Favour, as the Caſe is now (God be praiſed) hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily altered, ſo neither is this the intent of the Text, it being only an Emphatical Expreſſion to ſhew the Greatneſs of a Kings Power, and how inſolent a thing it is, to queſtion him in the juſt Exerciſe of his Regal Authority, whilſt he is Executing the <hi>Laws</hi> of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41855:7"/>Country, for the puniſhment of Evil Doers, and for the Praiſe of them that Do Well, why ſhould any one oppoſe him? But if he be ſetting Fire to a City, ſubverting his Government, betraying his People, or deſtroying himſelf: One need not ask indeed what he is a doing, for the thing ſpeaks it ſelf; He is throwing off his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> and Reſiſtance is the only way to keep it on. This ſhould be endeavoured with all the reſpect to a Crowned Head, that the matter will bear; but if Force be neceſſary, it muſt be uſed. They are good Subjects that prevent their <hi>King's</hi> falling down a Precipice tho' it be by violent Hands; but they are <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> who out of Reſpect and Reverence will let him break his Neck. And we have the Authority of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and of the Learned <hi>Barclay, That where a</hi> King <hi>has no Authority, there he ceaſes to be</hi> King, <hi>and returns to the ſtate of a private</hi> Man. But call him <hi>King</hi> ſtill, if you pleaſe, it is however the Duty of his <hi>Council,</hi> and thoſe about him, who have opportunity, to admoniſh him of Danger, and prevent his Ruine as far as they can, before it be too late. And perhaps the miſ-applying of this very Text, may have made ſome Men over-Cautious, and deprived <hi>Kings</hi> of that free and wholeſome Advice which might have been eatly ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to them.</p>
            <p>Let us now look into the Scriptures, and ſee whether what has been ſaid to <hi>Kings</hi> in former times, may not ſeem to counter-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance this Interrogative, <hi>What doeſt thou? Samuel</hi> told <hi>King Saul,</hi> he <hi>had done fooliſhly,</hi> and charges him with Diſobedience, Stubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Rebellion. <hi>Eliſah</hi> told <hi>King Ahab,</hi> That <hi>he had ſold him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to do evil in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> and that it was <hi>he and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe that troubled Iſrael.</hi> Theſe are Reproofs to the purpoſe, and certainly of no leſs importance than to ſay, <hi>What doeſt thou?</hi> Now it is to be ſuppoſed that God would inſpire his <hi>Prophets</hi> to ſpeak ſuch words to their <hi>Kings,</hi> as were not fit to be ſpoken by others upon the like Occaſion? So that I conclude, this Text hinders not at all, but that a <hi>King</hi> pulling down the <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Law,</hi> and ſetting up <hi>Superſtition, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> may be queſtioned and gainſaid by his Council, and reſiſted too, by the Majority of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Another Text, which is wont to be urged for the Power and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credneſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41855:8"/>of <hi>Kings,</hi> is <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. <hi>By me Kings reign, and Princes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree Justice:</hi> But I never hear them read the Context, <hi>by me Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the Earth:</hi> And good reaſon, for this would prove too much, and more than they would have, namely, that <hi>Judges</hi> are <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> as well as <hi>Kings;</hi> for by the ſame <hi>Logick</hi> that the one is inferred from the 15th Verſe, the other will follow from the 16th Verſe; I challenge any one to ſhew me the difference. This would have been ſtrange Doctrine in the late <hi>Reign,</hi> when <hi>Durante Beneplacito</hi> came into faſhion, and <hi>Judges</hi> were turn'd out for doing Right.</p>
            <p>But I do not ſee how either of the two can be proved from this Scripture: For who is this <hi>Me,</hi> and this <hi>I,</hi> mentioned here in my Text? It is not <hi>Solomon,</hi> for verſ. 23. <hi>I was ſet up from Everlaſting.</hi> Nor is it <hi>God</hi> himſelf, for at Verſ. 22. he ſays, <hi>The Lord poſſeſſed me in the beginning.</hi> But it is <hi>Wiſdom</hi> which is here ſpoken of, and which <hi>Solomon</hi> perſonates all along, ſpeaking in the firſt Perſon, from Verſe the 12th to the end of the Chapter; and ſetting forth the Nature and Excellency, the Power and Advantages of <hi>Wiſdom; I Wiſdom dwell with Prudence, &amp;c.</hi> and a little after, <hi>By me Kings reign,</hi> &amp;c. So then the plain meaning of the Text is this, That <hi>Kings</hi> reign by <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and that <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> who have the Adminiſtration of Publick Affairs, are qualified by <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the great Concerns and Buſineſs of a <hi>Kingdom;</hi> And tho' all <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of State are not thus qualified (which is the Cauſe of many ſhort and unfortunate Reigns) yet here we are taught what it is that qualifies them for <hi>Government,</hi> and that <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> is to be ſought by them more than fine <hi>Silver,</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> rather than choice <hi>Gold.</hi> If this Leſſon had been well learned by our late Kings, <hi>England</hi> had been a flouriſhing Nation at this day, and might perhaps have given <hi>Laws</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time our Adverſaries will be ready to demand, after their ſcoffing manner, When is it time for the People to <hi>Rebel?</hi> And who muſt judge between them and their <hi>King?</hi> To this I ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, after I have made an Obſervation about the word <hi>Rebel,</hi> or <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It has been oft obſerved by Learned Men, that the Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to humane Capacity, uſes ſuch Forms of Speech as are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41855:8"/>common among Men, tho' the ſame are not to be taken in a ſtrict and proper ſence. Thus it is ſaid <hi>God made two great Lights, the one to Rule the Day, the other to Rule the Night;</hi> whereas it is certain that the <hi>Moon</hi> has no more light in it ſelf than a Stone-Wall; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſhines by reflecting to us that borrowed Light it receives from the <hi>Sun.</hi> So when a People Arm themſelves againſt their <hi>King,</hi> it is very obvious to call it <hi>Rebellion,</hi> tho their Cauſe be never ſo juſt: And it ſeems to me, that the Scripture in ſundry places ſpeaks after the ſame manner, calling that <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which ſtrictly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly is not ſo, or which at leaſt is not <hi>Rebellion</hi> in a Criminal Senſe.</p>
            <p>This perhaps may ſeem ſtrange to ſome People; but let them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially conſider 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.19. where it is ſaid, <hi>Iſrael rebelled againſt the Houſe of David unto this Day:</hi> And to this Day they were never reproved for it; and good reaſon, <hi>For this thing is from Me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> by the Prophet <hi>Shemaiah,</hi> verſ. 24. Nor can we call this a bare Permiſſion, but it was Determined before-hand, and a Prophet ſent to <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to give him Notice of it, <hi>Beheld I will rend the Kingdom out of the hand of</hi> Solomon, <hi>and will give Ten Tribes to thee,</hi> 1 Kings 11.31. And why ſhould God do this? <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they have for ſaken me and worſhipped Idols,</hi> &amp;c. So that here is a peremptory Decree for this Defection, with the Reaſon annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and God ordered ſeeond Cauſes ſo as to bring it about. Learned Men may diſpute, if they pleaſe, whether the Ten Tribes were free Agents in what they did; it is evident from the Text, That this Revolt of theirs was the Purpoſe and Deſign of <hi>God,</hi> and was approved by him, tho' it is called in Scripture <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Inſtance of this kind we have in 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.7. where it is ſaid of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> That <hi>he rebelled againſt the King of Aſſria.</hi> Was <hi>Hezekiah</hi> an Offender in this? No, <hi>for the Lord was with him.</hi> Whatever Promiſes or Covenants had paſſed between him and the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> we know not: This is certain, That King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> did well in throwing off the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Yoke, tho' it hath the name of <hi>Rebellion; for he clave to the Lord and departed not from following him, but kept his commandments. So that after him was none like him among all the Kings</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> nor any <hi>that were before him.</hi> Behold here a Sinleſs <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which was the thing I aim'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41855:9"/>at; and now let the <hi>Jacobites</hi> call us <hi>Rebells</hi> or what Elſe they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now proceed to give my Anſwer, when it is time to <hi>Rebel:</hi> having firſt declared when it is not time. It is not to fly to <hi>Arms</hi> for ſome few private Injuries done to particular perſons, whilſt Law has its due Courſe in the Main, and the Vital parts of <hi>Government</hi> remain ſafe. Indeed people are ſeldom forward to hazard their own Lives and Fortunes to Revenge private wrongs. Nor yet ought they to Embroil a <hi>Kingdom</hi> for ſome publick Miſcarriages of the <hi>King,</hi> when it may be reaſonably ſuppoſ'd, that he hath Us'd his Prerogative for the good of his people, to the beſt of his Judgment, tho' in Effect it hath proved Contrary. What is well meant, and will afford a tollerable reaſon, ſhould be forgiven, notwithſtanding the ill Conſequence, when it is not wilfully perſiſted in. There is a time for Prayers as well as for Self-defence, and that ſhould be try'd in the firſt place; and ſo long as any hope remains, it is a proper Seaſon for Faith and Patience.</p>
            <p>But when the <hi>Kings</hi> Illegal Proceedings have Extended one way or other to the Majority of the People, and from particular injuries have advanced to an invaſion upon all mens <hi>Liberties;</hi> When the Violence that has affected many, is of ſuch a Nature and Conſequence as to threaten All; When High-Commiſſion-Courts are ſet up to diſſeiz Men of their <hi>Free-holds,</hi> and <hi>Charters</hi> call'd in for packing of <hi>Parliaments;</hi> When honeſt <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are every where turn'd out, and ſworn Enemies to the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> fill their places; When we are threatned, like the <hi>Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites,</hi> to be Chaſtized with Scorpions, and Foreign <hi>Cut-throats</hi> like to be let in among us; When <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Property, Life</hi> and <hi>Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> are almoſt within the Jaws of a Gaping <hi>Monſter;</hi> When all the Foundations, and the whole Frame of <hi>Government</hi> are ſo ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that Diſſolution muſt enſue; When there is no hope left, nor any Counſel can be heard but <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and bigotted <hi>Papiſts;</hi> And to compleat all, when all Men are ſenſible, and three quarters at leaſt of the Nation are perſwaded in their Conſciences that all this is really ſo: If ever Men will ſtand up for Self-Defence, and to ſave Poſterity, <hi>This is the Time.</hi> When Matters are brought to this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41855:9"/>paſs, to talk of Paſſive <hi>Obedience,</hi> is the greateſt Nonſenſe in the World; and to tell the People of being ſubject to Authority, when there is no Authority, but Illegal Force, and all the Rules and Meaſures of Government broken, is to talk to the Wind, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Men to be tamely <hi>Murder'd</hi> in Obedience to Illegal <hi>Violence. Rebellion</hi> in this Caſe (as they pleaſe to call it) becomes a <hi>Duty;</hi> and to be <hi>Paſſive,</hi> is to Betray the Nation. And then for the other part of the Queſtion about a <hi>Judge,</hi> there is none upon Earth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine this Matter, but the <hi>Sword.</hi> Every Man will Judge for himſelf, and Conſult as he can for his own Safety: But there lies no Appeal, but only to the Court of <hi>Heaven</hi> for the Succeſs of the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> and that Court (<hi>God</hi> be praiſed) has determin'd the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by ſending us a <hi>King</hi> that Maintains our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Ancient Government.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41855:10"/>
            <head>PART II. A DEFENCE OF THE Foregoing DISCOURSE AGAINST Certain Exceptions Communicated in Writing.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Paper of Exceptions againſt what I have been ſaying hitherto, in behalf of the preſent <hi>Government,</hi> and in Defence of the late Happy <hi>Revolution:</hi> But I am ſorry you ſhould trouble your ſelf and me with ſo many trite and common things, which have had full and ſufficient Anſwers <hi>uſque ad Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeam:</hi> However ſince you ſeem to expect it, I ſhall go thro' them all, and doubt not to ſatisfie any indifferent Perſon. But ſuch as are, or ſeem to be under Judicial Blindneſs and Infatuation, may ſeek for Conviction by <hi>Miracle,</hi> if they pleaſe; and 'tis a queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that would do it: For they do not appear to be capable of any Satisfaction, till they find it in the ſmart of the <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which they have long been Courting and Admiring, and are now grown Impatient of Delay. But of you I hoped better things, and ſhall be ſorry to find my ſelf miſtaken.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41855:10"/>
The firſt thing I meet with is this; <hi>But what, I pray, if Kings miſdemean themſelves in their Government, muſt they preſently ceaſe to be Kings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You put this <hi>Queſtion,</hi> as if you had not read what you are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Anſwer, without taking any notice of what I quoted you from K. <hi>James</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barclay,</hi> and ſo you go on as if nothing at all had been ſaid in this Matter.</p>
            <p>Therefore I proceed to</p>
            <p>The next thing; <hi>God Almighty made them Kings, and how can leſs Authority Dethrone them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is no better than pure <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> as if <hi>Kings</hi> were not of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nane Race, but made in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſent down upon <hi>Earth</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour Mortals, like ſo many <hi>Frogs</hi> to be eaten up by a <hi>Stork</hi> without any hopes of Deliverance. What would you think if I ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance this for an Argument, <hi>God</hi> makes <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Lawyers;</hi> therefore <hi>Merchants</hi> cannot break, nor <hi>Lawyers</hi> prevaricate. I am ſure <hi>Kings</hi> are not made without Means no more than other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men: All is Providence, from the Throne to the Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil; and we find in Scripture <hi>Kings</hi> made by the <hi>People.</hi> Nay even Hereditary <hi>Kings</hi> are made by the <hi>People</hi> as well as <hi>Elective:</hi> For Crowns, at this day, are not Intail'd by Meſſages from <hi>Heaven,</hi> but by <hi>Laws</hi> made upon <hi>Earth;</hi> and I pray who made theſe <hi>Laws?</hi> Had the People no Hand in them? Hiſtorians tell us, That the Right Deſcent of Engliſh <hi>Kings</hi> has been broken now Nine times ſince <hi>K. William</hi> the Firſt. And the Scriptures tell us, That the Lineaſ Succeſſion of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> have been Interrupted and cut off, ſometimes by expreſs Nomination from <hi>God</hi> by a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> and ſometimes alſo Providentially. <hi>Jehu,</hi> a Subject, was A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed <hi>King</hi> by a <hi>Prophet, Baaſha</hi> ſhew <hi>Nadab</hi> and Succeeded in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Omri</hi> was made <hi>King</hi> by the People without any Divine Appointment. So that here is <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> the <hi>Sword,</hi> and the <hi>People,</hi> each of them ſetting up their ſeveral <hi>King.</hi> And in a word, all <hi>Kings</hi> are made and unmade by Divine Providence, which outs down one and ſets up another; and we quarrel at this, and think much that God ſhould Rule the World, unleſs he give us a particular Account of his Ways.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41855:11"/>
But ſuppoſe they do really deſign the Subverſion of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who ſhall or ought to puniſh them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barclay</hi> ſays, in that Caſe, the <hi>King returns to the ſtate of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man, and the People become Free and Superior.</hi> This is ſo cutting a thing, eſpecially from one of your own Party, that I ſuppoſe you durſt not ſo much as touch it. But I Anſwer; None ought to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the <hi>King,</hi> nor to hurt his Perſon, tho' he be fall'n from his Power: But I ſay, that when a <hi>Government</hi> is breaking up, and all things at the brink of Ruin and Confuſion, every Man ought to ſtand for his Life, and to Defend his <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Poſterity,</hi> the beſt he can, from future <hi>Miſery;</hi> other wiſe they are guilty of Self-Murder, and of Betraying their Country, provided they be in a Condition to appear in the Field, as many Brave <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> did at <hi>York,</hi> and in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and other places of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in <hi>Nov.</hi> 1688. In the mean time, the <hi>King</hi> is to be Counſelled to keep within the Sanctuary of the <hi>Law,</hi> or at leaſt to keep his Perſon out of Danger, and not to Head his Party. But if he will, againſt all Juſtice, Prudence, and Perſwaſions, Join with Wicked Men, and Expoſe himſelf to Blind <hi>Bullets,</hi> and fall in the <hi>Field,</hi> it is to be lookt upon as an Accidental thing, and none can help it. <hi>God</hi> forbid that any one ſhould think of hurting him on purpoſe; and Charge ſhould be given to all to beware as much as poſſible of ſo doing. For this, ſee further that Nameleſs, but very Learned Book, which your ſelf put into my Hands.</p>
            <p>You come next to your Boys Play, Give a thing and take a thing; where from a certain <hi>Maxim</hi> of your Learned <hi>Politician,</hi> you infer, that the People have wholly and intirely diveſted themſelves of all their <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> without any Limitation whatſoever, and therefore they can by no means call for it back again.</p>
            <p>I cannot deny at this time of Day, that a Free People may make themſelves <hi>Slaves</hi> by Conſent: There are thoſe among us, who not only ſeem forward to do it, but take it ill that the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will not do the like. Hitherto I have thought it impoſſible that any Wiſe Man ſhould do an Act without having ſome end in it; or ſhould give up his whole Right to the <hi>Will</hi> of another, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpect back again upon himſelf. But the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> whoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are Unaccountable, have given us a Demonſtration of it, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41855:11"/>to them only are we Indebted for ſo Noble a Diſcovery. I could wiſh they would try the Experiment in <hi>France,</hi> and not trouble us here in <hi>England,</hi> who are under better Circumſtances. Indeed thoſe that have made an ill Bargain, muſt be content to ſtand by it, till they can be releaſed: But we have made a good one, and will ſtand for it, not doubting the performance on either part. We have Sworn Allegiance to the <hi>King,</hi> and he has Sworn to Rule by <hi>Law;</hi> Allegiance and Protection are Correlatives, and will be ſo while this <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſtands: Take away the one, and the other falls to the Ground. But no <hi>Scheme</hi> of Politicks will pleaſe you, but that of <hi>Holbs,</hi> or <hi>Filmer,</hi> which teacheth <hi>Kings</hi> to break through the moſt Sacred and Solemn <hi>Obligations,</hi> and to Act <hi>Leviathan</hi> without Controul.</p>
            <p>Your laſt Argument was <hi>Argumentum Puerile,</hi> taken from Boys Play; the next is <hi>Argumentum Peſtiferum,</hi> taken from the Common Peſts of the Nation, as you are pleaſed to ſtyle the poor <hi>Bailiffs;</hi> and thus you expreſs it.</p>
            <p>As to the Power in not being reſiſted in the Execution of the <hi>Laws,</hi> which you are pleaſed to allow to <hi>Kings,</hi> if that be all they are <hi>Kings</hi> for; truly I think they are in a far worſe ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than the Common Peſts of the Nation, the Rogue <hi>Bailiffs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by your Favour, I did not ſay, that is all they are <hi>Kings</hi> for, but I ſaid the <hi>King</hi> in Executing the Law is not to be Reſiſted, not denying him his proper ſhare in the <hi>Legiſlative Power,</hi> in which none will oppoſe him: But if he ſhould aſſume the whole Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power, as ſome in Effect have done, that would mightily alter the Caſe. But beſides all this, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> has a <hi>Royal Prerogative,</hi> which is not a Diſpenſing Power, or a Power above the <hi>Law</hi> to do what he pleaſes; but it is a Power Reſiding in the <hi>King,</hi> partly defin'd and limitted by the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, and partly left to the <hi>King</hi>'s Wiſdom and Clemency, to be exerted for the Benefit of the Subject, where the edge of the <hi>Law</hi> is too ſharp, which often happens by Caſualty or Humane Infirmity. For the <hi>Law</hi> is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Rule,</hi> but in many Caſes it may be defeated; nor can it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for all future Accidents. Infirmity or Knavery in Witneſſes may occaſion a wrong Sentence: And <hi>Laws</hi> can never be made ſo compleat, but that <hi>Summum Jus</hi> may happen to be <hi>Summa Injuria.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:41855:12"/>So that the <hi>King's</hi> Prerogative is to Relieve the Subject in Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Caſes, and being uſed with Prudence and good Advice, is a Glorious <hi>Jewel</hi> of the <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now purſue the Compariſon between an Engliſh <hi>Monarch</hi> and a <hi>Bailiff:</hi> The one let us View upon a <hi>Throne,</hi> Cloathed with Power and Excellent <hi>Majeſty,</hi> Veſted with a Noble Prerogative, and giving his Royal Aſſent to <hi>Laws</hi> made for the Puniſhment of Evil-doers, and for the Praiſe of them that do well: Or let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider him in the Field giving <hi>Laws</hi> to <hi>Princes,</hi> Commanding many Thouſands, Protecting the Innocent, Defending the <hi>Faith,</hi> Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his Enemies, and for ſeveral Years together Defying the <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> and Deſiring Nothing more than to meet him fairly in the Field. Now what is there in a <hi>Bailiff,</hi> to bear up the Credit of ſuch a Compariſon? He is indeed a Lawful and Neceſſary <hi>Officer,</hi> but I know not how it comes to paſs that he ſhould not only be a <hi>Rogue,</hi> but the Common <hi>Peſt</hi> of the Nation. If this be a mean Character of a <hi>Bailiff</hi> (as I think it is) what muſt it be of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who (becauſe he is not Arbitrary) is in a far worſe State and Condition? This is a vile Reflection upon the Engliſh Frame of <hi>Government,</hi> which many Wiſe Men think is the beſt Conſtitution in the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here comes the Old Killing Queſtion, as briskly as if it had never yet been Anſwered; Who muſt be <hi>Judge</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> has a Deſign to Subvert the <hi>Government?</hi> And 'tis brought in with theſe Triumphant words; <hi>You ſee,</hi> Sir, <hi>what a goodly thing you have made of your ſo much boaſted Cauſe and Demonſtration of Nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ſome People thro' <hi>Blindneſs,</hi> and others thro' <hi>Prejudice,</hi> are not capable of a Demonſtration. <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> I will venture my Paper and yours before any Learned Men, even tho' he be a <hi>Jacobite,</hi> and will for once be Judged by him, whether your Cauſe or mine is better Managed. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> You have in my Paper a full Anſwer to this very Queſtion; but you do ſo abound in your own Senſe, that you could not ſee it; or perhaps indeed you have not read it, for haſte to get my Paper Anſwered, I ſhall therefore Anſwer it once more with ſome ſmall Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I ſay then, theſe very Three Parties you mention, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41855:12"/>the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>People,</hi> and a <hi>Forreigner,</hi> are all of them Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Judges</hi> in this Matter.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Firſt,</hi> Cannot the <hi>King</hi> eaſily tell what he himſelf Deſigns to do? Certainly he is a Competent <hi>Judge</hi> of his own <hi>Mind</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, whether he declare it or not. K. <hi>James</hi> ſaid in his Firſt Council, he would Maintain the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and many well-meaning People were ſo ſimple as to believe him: Yet not long after it was declared in a private Letter (ſaid to be his) <hi>That he would Reduce the Kingdom to the Catholick Religion, or Die a Martyr.</hi> But whether this be true or no, every Man certainly is a proper <hi>Judge</hi> of his own Intention, but he is not like to diſcover the ſame, when ſuch Diſcovery may be a Means to prevent his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The People too are Judges in this Caſe: For cannot every Man tell what he feels, and what he fears? When a Man's <hi>Head</hi> is broken, or his <hi>Goods</hi> taken from him, he has reaſon to know that it is ſo; and his Neighbour that is a Spectator to Day, may be a Sufferer to Morrow. <hi>Jam proximus ardet,</hi> is <hi>Scarborough</hi> Warning. If a <hi>Charter</hi> be taken from a <hi>Corporation,</hi> are the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple no Judges as to Matter of Fact? If the <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Fellows</hi> of the <hi>Colledge</hi> are turn'd out of their <hi>Freehold,</hi> muſt ſome body elſe Judge for them, and inform them that they want <hi>Lodgings?</hi> If a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Juſtice</hi> of Peace be turn'd out of Commiſſion, and a <hi>Papiſt</hi> put in his room, he certainly knows that he is not on the <hi>Bench,</hi> and is capable of making a Rational Judgment, not only of the Matter of Fact, but of the Conſequence. If I ſee a <hi>Cut-throat</hi> Murdering my Neighbour, and then making towards me with his long <hi>Knife,</hi> you would have me to ſtay till my Throat be cut, before I muſt judge what his meaning is. In ſhort, your whole driſt is to make the <hi>King</hi> an <hi>Idol,</hi> and the People <hi>Sots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to a <hi>Forreigner,</hi> or Neighbouring <hi>Prince,</hi> 'tis very poſſible, that he may make as true a Judgment as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: A By ſtander ſees how the Game goes better ſometimes than he that plays it. And it is well that it was ſo in our Caſe of late, elſe you and I might have been Diſputing in a Dungeon, or a worſe place; for which all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and true <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> ought to give Thanks to <hi>God,</hi> and next to Him, to our Gracious Deliverer, K.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41855:13"/>
               <hi>William.</hi> Thus you may ſee, if Prejudice will permit, that after all your flouriſhing, each of the three Parties you except againſt, are, or at leaſt may be; proper Judges in the Caſe before us.</p>
            <p>But indeed I thought at firſt your Queſtion had been this, <hi>When a difference breaks out between the King and his People, who is a proper Judge to determine the matter between them?</hi> For it is one thing to judge Rationally, and almoſt infallibly, when ill Deſigns are on foot; and another thing to judge between the Parties at odds, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Difference. As to the former, I believe that even your ſelf did once judge that we were in an evil <hi>Caſe,</hi> and ſo, I am ſure, did moſt of the <hi>Jacobites;</hi> and now you long to be ſo again, or in a worſe: But in the latter Caſe there is no Judge upon Earth; and this I alſo told you before. There lies no <hi>Appeal</hi> but to the Court of <hi>Heaven,</hi> nor any way to plead the Cauſe, but with the <hi>Sword;</hi> and the God of Battel, that gives Victory, muſt Judge and Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Controverſie. But this is always to be underſtood when all other means have been tried.
<q>For if the Caſe will admit of Intreaties, ſober Counſels, or Legal Appeals, they are to be uſed: But if there be no room for theſe, or if they take no place, but illegal force be uſed; that force may, nay muſt be reſiſted, or Evil is conſented to: For he that will not ſerve the Publick by that means, when there is no other, does actually conſent to the ruine of it, and is a Betrayer of his Country.</q> 
               <hi>They are Rebels</hi> (ſays a Learned Author) <hi>who Arm againſt the Government, and not they who Arm to defend it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, you ſay, That <hi>if a King do give Authority to Rogues, and that too under his Broad Seal, to cut any of his Subjects Throats, be they more or fewer, ſuch Perſons may reſiſt ſuch illegal force, in defence of their Lives, and kill their Aſſailants too, if they be able, and justify the ſame by the Eſtabliſh'd</hi> Laws <hi>of the</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>Admirably well! Right every Word. See here the force of <hi>Truth,</hi> that cannot be ſtifled under the greateſt prejudice. This is all the <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> I contend for. Did ever any one plead for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance</hi> of Lawful <hi>Authority?</hi> No ſure: It is only the <hi>Kings</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Commands that may be reſiſted, not his Lawful Ones. Yet you conclude this Point with the moſt Comical Fancy in the world; you ſay, <hi>I have brought my Hogs to a fair Market;</hi> when on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41855:13"/>you do here juſtify all that I have ſaid, or can ſay upon this <hi>Argument,</hi> and you have given up your <hi>Cauſe</hi> to all intents. Since I was born, did I never ſee ſuch a Concluſion from ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p>You ſeem to take exception that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>The King is King by Law,</hi> but you do not well explain your ſelf, nor tell me where your Exception lies. Yet you urge that <hi>Maxim</hi> of the <hi>Law, That the King can do no wrong,</hi> as if it were on your ſide, which makes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as much againſt you; for theſe two Expreſſions are of the ſame importance, it being all one in effect, to ſay he is <hi>King by Law,</hi> and to ſay, <hi>He can do no wrong.</hi> For what's the reaſon that the <hi>King,</hi> being but a <hi>Man,</hi> can do no wrong? It is not becauſe he does not do amiſs in granting illegal Commiſſions; for no doubt he ſins in it, and does that which is <hi>Morally Evil:</hi> But the reaſon is, becauſe he can act nothing, <hi>qua Rex,</hi> but by or according to <hi>Law;</hi> So that unleſs the <hi>Law</hi> be wrong, the <hi>King</hi> can do none. From whence it naturally follows, that whatſoever the <hi>King</hi> does beſide or Contrary to the <hi>Law,</hi> is not the Act of a <hi>King</hi> but of a private perſon.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe, for Example, a <hi>King</hi> at one time Corrects a <hi>Servant</hi> moderately for a real Fault, at another time he beats him ſeverely without a Cauſe, and the third time he kills him without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation: Theſe are none of them <hi>Regal Acts;</hi> for the <hi>Firſt</hi> he does as Maſter of a <hi>Family;</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> as a Man in <hi>Paſsion;</hi> the <hi>Third,</hi> as a <hi>Tyrant.</hi> Yet I do not ſay that this Tyrannical Act <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkings</hi> him: For one Act makes not a Habit, and 'tis poſſible he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of it, and lay it ſo to heart, as to become a better Man and a better <hi>King</hi> ever after. But this I do ſay, That a conſtant Courſe of <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Proceeding, ſo far as to lay aſide the <hi>Laws,</hi> and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Change the Government, does <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nking</hi> him; and the reaſon is, becauſe he deſtroys that by which he has his being: It is the <hi>Law</hi> makes him a <hi>King,</hi> which being removed and laid aſide, he has no Foundation to ſtand upon. This I ſaid before, and by your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it is not <hi>Gratis Dictum,</hi> as you are pleaſed to ſay, but you have Anſwered my paper without reading it, or at leaſt without regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what you Read.</p>
            <p>Nor is this a Parallel Caſe with that which you put, of whipping
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41855:14"/>your Boy too Severely, and thereupon ceaſing to be his <hi>Father:</hi> There is a wide difference between the Diſſolution of a <hi>Government</hi> and the Correction of a <hi>Child,</hi> the one is <hi>Deſtroyed</hi> and the other <hi>Improved;</hi> But if you deſtroy your <hi>Child,</hi> that is, kill him by Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting him, this will bring the Compariſon nearer home. For as a <hi>King</hi> Ceaſes to be a <hi>King</hi> when he has deſtroyed his <hi>Kingdom:</hi> So a <hi>Father</hi> ceaſes to be a <hi>Father</hi> when he has no <hi>Child.</hi> So that your own Compariſon with a little improvement makes altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. Beſides there is a manifeſt difference between a <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and a <hi>Political</hi> Relation: The one can never be diſſolved while the parties are in being, but the other may. A good <hi>King</hi> may happen to loſe his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and remain in Exile, that I know you'l readily grant: But he that Succeeds him in the Adminiſtration of <hi>Sovereign power</hi> is <hi>King,</hi> at leaſt <hi>de Facto,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> requires <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> to be paid him, ſo that the former relation Ceaſes. But this puts me in mind to recommend to you Sr. <hi>Ro. Filmers,</hi> Political <hi>Babel,</hi> whereof this is the Corner Stone, <hi>that we are all born Slaves, and that a Son, a Subject, a Servant and a Slave, are all one, without any Difference.</hi> If you are not yet acquainted with that worthy <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> its great pity you ſhould not, for I believe you would greatly admire him.</p>
            <p>You tell me next, To bring the Authority of K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt is all over <hi>Jargon,</hi> with a great deal more to the ſame purpoſe; where you make Reflections upon that Learned <hi>King,</hi> ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ſo falſe, that it will be a kindneſs to you to ſuppreſs them, I ſhall only hint at Two Things, and paſs on. <hi>Firſt,</hi> You ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that theſe imprudent Sayings, (as you imprudently call them) were ſpoken to Court the People at his coming to the <hi>Crown,</hi> and you will find them in the Ninth Year of his Reign. <hi>Secondly,</hi> This is the firſt time that I have heard the Cauſe of our <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> and the Crime of K. <hi>Charles's Munder,</hi> laid at his Door. I rather think with ſubmiſſion to better <hi>Judgments,</hi> that if his <hi>Cautions</hi> had been obſerved, it might have been a means to prevent the <hi>Evils</hi> following.</p>
            <p>You approve, it ſeems, of thoſe Determinations made in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at ſeveral times, namely, under Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, with the Judgment of <hi>Archbiſhop
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41855:14"/>Laud,</hi> according as I ſet it down before, for you ſay you cannot but grant it very <hi>Lawful.</hi> And I tell you once more, you have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely given up your <hi>Cauſe;</hi> for I cannot underſtand how any thing can go higher in Defence of the Late <hi>Revolution.</hi> But you go on with the greateſt Confidence in the World, ſaying. It was to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a <hi>Rebellion</hi> begun by the Subjects; <hi>Cujus contrarium verum eſt,</hi> it was to ſtop the <hi>Incroachments</hi> of <hi>Princes</hi> upon their <hi>Subjects.</hi> But this it is to write before you read; the words are theſe, <hi>When a Prince breaks in upon the Religion and Liberties of his People, they ought to ſtand up in their own Defence, and may alſo Call in a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to their Aſſiſtance.</hi> This you may find upon Record, and taken notice of by ſeveral Learned Men of late. See eſpecially the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Mask,</hi> ſuppoſed to be written by Dr. <hi>C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place you falſifie my words, to make me ſpeak what I was not thinking of; and you jumble together a deal of <hi>Nonſenſe,</hi> and would have me to own it; concluding with your uſual <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, This you'l ſay your ſelf</hi> (I ſuppoſe) <hi>needs no Confutation.</hi> So indeed I do, and with very good Reaſon, for 'tis your own <hi>Stuff,</hi> and none of mine. And thus it follows;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You cannot but Wonder that a Man of my parts, &amp;c. Should make no Difference betwine a people Rebelling againſt their Lawful King, and a people Rebelling againſt God,</hi> when there is no ſuch paſſage to be found, nor any thing like it. My words are theſe, <hi>So long as a King remains a King, and Maintains the Laws, he is a Rebel that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes him: But when he falls from that, he is a Rebel himſelf.</hi> For this I quoted the place (as may be ſeen) 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.32. where <hi>Samuel</hi> Charges <hi>Saul,</hi> with <hi>Rebellion.</hi> And I now add, that a <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is as much obliged to Govern by <hi>Law,</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſfrael</hi> was to obſerve <hi>God's Commands.</hi> As for the Story of <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eck,</hi> It is only toucht upon to bring in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s ſevere Reproof and <hi>Davids</hi> taking <hi>Arms</hi> againſt him.</p>
            <p>But ſay you, <hi>Saul</hi> was at that Inſtant rejected from his <hi>Kingdom.</hi> What trifling is this! He was <hi>King</hi> ſo long as he liv'd, and <hi>David</hi> was his Subject, never pretending to the <hi>Crown</hi> in his liſe time, yet he took <hi>Arms</hi> to defend himſelf: And his behaviour towards <hi>Saul</hi> is a good Example both ways; Namely, of Dutiful reſpect towards the <hi>King,</hi> in ſparing his <hi>Perſon</hi> and giving him Honour and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41855:15"/>And at the ſame time in taking care of his own <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Security.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I agree with you, that all poſſible Reſpect ſhould be paid to the Perſons of <hi>Kings:</hi> But I would not have them flattered, nor taught to be <hi>Arbitrary.</hi> I would not have them told that <hi>Subjects</hi> have nothing of their own, not ſo much as their <hi>Souls;</hi> that they are only the <hi>Kings Vaſſals</hi> and <hi>Slaves,</hi> and that he may take their Lives and ſeiz their Fortunes at his pleaſure; that <hi>God</hi> made <hi>Kings,</hi> and no body can unmake them, nor ought to oppoſe them, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they do: ſuch <hi>Flattery</hi> and <hi>Sycophantry</hi> makes <hi>Kings</hi> firſt aſpire, and then tumble.</p>
            <p>I come now to a <hi>Greek Word,</hi> which is here employ'd to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but only to ſhew that you are a <hi>Learn'd Man,</hi> which I knew before: And here you affront the plain Letter of the Scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch haſt that you could not turn to the place I quoted. I ſhall wonder no more at your inſulting over me, when the <hi>Word of God</hi> can not be quiet for you.</p>
            <p>The buſineſs was this: Whereas the <hi>Jacobites</hi> love to call us <hi>Rebels,</hi> I undertook to ſhew that there was a ſinleſs <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and that the word was not always taken in an ill ſence; for this I quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 18.7. where it was ſaid <hi>the Lord was with him,</hi> (viz. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi>) <hi>and he</hi> Rebelled <hi>againſt the King of</hi> Aſſyria, <hi>and ſerved him not;</hi> and you ſay it was not certainly <hi>Rebellion:</hi> Now whether muſt <hi>Your Authority,</hi> or the <hi>Scripture,</hi> carry it? If you had ſaid this is not to be taken ſtrictly, then you had come to an Agreement with me, as to that matter, and there needed no words about it; but that you cannot endure; I am to be run down at any rate, and that with <hi>Triumph,</hi> when you have not ſaid one word to refute me. And all along I obſerve, that when you have the leaſt to ſay, you are the moſt confident: I conclude this in the <hi>Style</hi> which you except againſt; <hi>So the People of</hi> England <hi>Rebelled againſt K.</hi> James, <hi>for God was with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now draw near to the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of your Paper, where after many Windings and Doubles, like a <hi>Hare</hi> run almoſt to Death, I had you where we ſtarted, namely, at the <hi>Act forbidding to Arm againſt the King, upon any pretence whatſoever.</hi> I gave you four Reaſons at large to ſhew that theſe words could not poſſibly be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41855:15"/>without a tacit <hi>Reſervation:</hi> Nor have you offer'd ought that looks like an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to any of them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> you have quite omitted. To the <hi>Second,</hi> you have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought a Compariſon between an <hi>Engliſh Monarch</hi> and a <hi>Bayliff,</hi> ſhewing that the <hi>King</hi> is by great odds the worſe Man of the two. The <hi>Third</hi> you have fairly yielded, and therein given up your Cauſe. To the <hi>Fourth,</hi> you take Exception that I ſhould ſay, <hi>The King is King by Law;</hi> and yet you own the Maxim, <hi>That the King can do no Wrong.</hi> And now after all (ſuſpecting perhaps your Weakneſs and Inconſiſtence hitherto) you come to offer ſomething that looks at firſt ſight like a <hi>Dilemma,</hi> but unfortunately it wants one of its <hi>Members,</hi> which it ſeems you have dropt in great precipitation.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance of the matter is this: <hi>Either the Parliament did conſider the Conſequence of making ſuch a Law, or they did not: If not,</hi> (ſay you) <hi>they were a Club of</hi> Blockheads <hi>and meer</hi> Loggerheads. Very good! Here's the Conſequence of that. But what if the <hi>Parliament</hi> did conſider, what then? Why then (you ſay) <hi>you have in a few words run through all I have ſaid in this Cauſe:</hi> An admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conſequence, and a rare <hi>Dilemma!</hi> The one is lame of a ſide, and the other is <hi>falſe,</hi> unleſs you have run through my Papers with ſome ſmall <hi>Needle,</hi> which I cannot perceive.</p>
            <p>But let us Come once more to the Merits of the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> I grant the <hi>Parliament</hi> might, and I believe they did conſider the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of both ſides, that is, with reſpect to the <hi>King</hi> and the People. And tho' tis poſſible they might compute amiſs, yet I rather incline to thinke they did not: For Either they muſt Speak in General <hi>terms,</hi> or elſe they muſt make ſome Limitation or Exception. Now there is no Exception to be made, but only this, In caſe the <hi>King</hi> ſhould become a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and Endeavour to Subvert the <hi>Government:</hi> But how ſhameful and dangerous a thing muſt it have been to mention ſuch a thing in an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament!</hi> It might have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked the <hi>King</hi> to Diſſolve them, or it might have prepared the people for a new <hi>Rebellion.</hi> So that ſuppoſing it neceſſary to paſs ſuch an <hi>Act,</hi> it muſt of Neceſſity paſs in general <hi>Terms,</hi> tho' it may ſeem hard upon the people. But it is not hard upon them at all, being underſtood in ſuch a Senſe as to be Conſiſtent with other <hi>Laws:</hi> And either it muſt be ſo underſtood or it does Actually
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41855:16"/>change the <hi>Government,</hi> and gives the <hi>King</hi> a deſpotick <hi>Power,</hi> which that the <hi>Parliament</hi> did ever deſign, is Nonſenſe to Imagine.</p>
            <p>I am now at the foot of the Account, and you think you have given me a full Anſwer, deſiring me to look once more over my Papers, and tell you, if you are not Miſtaken in your Anſwers. I have told you already, and now I tell you again, that you are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily miſtaken, and I ſhall never be made to think otherwiſe. I have looks over my Papers, and yours too, ſeveral times, which you I believe, have not done once, or if at all, I am ſure without due Conſideration. But you were ſo Ambitious to anſwer my Papers all at one Sitting, that you had far better have let it alone. Many things you have left Untoucht, and thoſe you have, are no worſe for your handling. Amongſt the reſt, I wonder you have taken no Notice of what I quoted you out of the famous <hi>Barclay,</hi> ſo great an Aſſerter of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> that he is Reckoned the head of your party: And yet no writing that I have ſeen has determined this point more directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. You have Ruffled the Memory of his <hi>Royal Maſter</hi> with a witneſs, and 'tis ſtrange that he alſo ſhould not come in for a Caſt of your <hi>Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, Sir, If I were worthy to adviſe you, I ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that you would forbear idle company, and not ſpend your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney on thoſe that poiſon and corrupt you; that you would think more, and talk leſs, and read with conſideration ſuch Books as are written on this ſubject by <hi>Men</hi> of the greateſt Learning and Piety, and particularly that which you lent me; that you would ſcribble no more in this manner <hi>quicquid in Buccam venerit,</hi> and think with your ſelf whether you be fit to cope with the greateſt Men in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> For I have ſaid nothing here, but what ſuch have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, tho not in the ſame words, yet in far better. However, being <hi>Challeng'd</hi> at firſt, and now again <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rg'd</hi> with ſo much <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and <hi>Triumph,</hi> I would not wholly decline the <hi>Argument,</hi> and doubt not to defend it againſt the beſt of your <hi>Party.</hi> I call it your <hi>Party,</hi> but <hi>I</hi> hope I ſhall have occaſion to retract that expreſſion; for <hi>I</hi> remember the time you were of another Opinion, and do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to find you ſo again: For I am perſwaded it is not of your own
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41855:16"/>proper <hi>Genius</hi> that you are what you are, or what you ſeem to be at preſent; but by having ſometimes your Converſation amongſt Men of <hi>Slaviſh, Debauch'd and Pernicious</hi> Principles: And this is the Caſe of a great many more, that were once well-affected to the preſent <hi>Government.</hi> But you have had the Advantage of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Education,</hi> and your Learning is beyond many of your Profeſſion, which alſo is one of the moſt <hi>Honourable</hi> and moſt <hi>Loyal:</hi> For, but few of your <hi>Brethren</hi> Comparatively are <hi>Jacobites.</hi> Be not you (I beſeech you) toſs'd to and fro with every wind of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> nor led away with the prating <hi>Confidence</hi> of Pragmatick <hi>Fellows.</hi> Conſider what a parcel of <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and Profligates weigh, being laid in the Ballance againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and other Reformed Churches, together with that vaſt Body of <hi>Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Lawyers,</hi> and Subſtantial <hi>Commoners</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> They are but like the <hi>Vermine</hi> in the <hi>Fable</hi> that would needs ſwell to the bigneſs of an <hi>OX.</hi> And they may burſt themſelves with their own Poiſon if they pleaſe, the <hi>Government</hi> does not care a Straw for 'em, nor do I fear that ever they will be able to hurt it. And ſo Fare you well.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
